A Guide to the Michael C. Rockefeller collection FA256
Rockefeller Archive Center
Michael C. Rockefeller collection
1938-1971
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Michael Clark
Gerbrands, A. A. (Adrianus Alexander) (1917-1997)
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
FA256
15 Cubic Feet
Scope and Contents note
This collection consists of a selection of papers and photographs from Michael C. Rockefeller, the youngest son of Nelson A. Rockefeller and Mary Clark Rockefeller, including materials from his two anthropological expeditions on behalf of Harvard Univsersity to the Asmat region of New Guinea in 1961.
In addition to correspondence between Michael and his father, the collection contains Michael's journals, field notes, sketches, reference materials, drafts of his thesis "Nelson W. Aldrich and Banking Reform," and photographs. There are also some files related to the search for Michael, following his accidental death during his second expedition in New Guinea in November 1961. However, the bulk of the records are expressions of condolences to Nelson A. Rockefeller from the general public.
The papers also include documentation of Michael C. Rockefeller's posthumously published book "The Asmat of New Guinea" (1967).
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of the RAC.
Asmat (Indonesian people); Anthropology
- Nelson A. Rockefeller personal, Family and Friends, 1938-1971; H; 10.3 Cubic Feet
  - Michael C. Rockefeller papers, 1938-1971; 1; 10.21 Cubic Feet
    - Michael Rockefeller - General, 1949-1961 (Box 94, Folder 952)
    - Michael and Steven Rockefeler - Venezuela Trip, 1955 Summer (Box 94, Folder 953)
      Scope and Contents
      Arrangements for trip to Venezeula; schedule; telegrams from NAR; correspondence with friends in IBEC.
    - Michael Rockefeller - Summer Plans, 1958 (Box 94, Folder 954)
      Correspondence re: job with IBEC, living arrangements for Michael in Puerto Rico
    - Michael Rockefeller - Gifts, 1938-1959 (Box 94, Folder 955)
      Gifts for JDR Jr.
    - Michael Rockefeller - Contributions, 1960 (Box 94, Folder 956)
      Helping Michael with his giving program for the for the following year.
    - Michael Rockefeller - JDR Jr. Correspondence, 1943-1959 (Box 94, Folder 957)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Appeals (Denied) (Box 94, Folder 958)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Posthumous Appeals (Box 94, Folder 959)
      Replied to by Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Correspondence with Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR) (Box 94, Folder 960)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Correspondence - Adri Gerbrands (Box 94, Folder 961)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Correspondence - Kari Heider (Box 94, Folder 962)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Correspondence - Sam Putnum (Box 94, Folder 963)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Correspondence - Wat Tyler (Box 94, Folder 964)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Correspondence - Sarah Woodman (Box 94, Folder 965)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Correspondence - Miscellaneous (Box 94, Folder 966)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR) Correspondence following disappearance (Box 95, Folder 967-968)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Rene Wassing and Victor de Bruyn, 1961 (Box 95, Folder 969)
      Correspondence re: museum in New Guinea; Michael Rockefeller letters to Rene Wassing, Victor de Bruyn and Dr. J. O. Breu re: planned trip to Asmat
    - Michael Rockefeller - Robert G. Gardner, 1961-1963 (Box 95, Folder 970)
      Director of film study center, Peabody Museum; correspondence re: Michael's notebooks, negatives, Asmat volume, expenses, NAR pledge.
    - Michael Rockefeller - F.R.J. Eibrink Jansen (Box 95, Folder 971)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR) New Guinea Trip, 1961 November (Box 95, Folder 972)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR) Press Conference with Rene Wassing, 1961 November (Box 95, Folder 973)
    - Michael Rockefeller Search - Print Items (Box 95, Folder 974)
    - Michael Rockefeller - First Asmat Trip, Diary, 1961 June (Box 95, Folder 975)
    - Michael Rockefeller Search - Letters of Appreciation - United States (Box 95, Folder 976)
    - Michael Rockefeller Search - Letters of Appreciation - New Guinea (Box 95, Folder 977)
      Letters to various people who helped in the search; officials and missionaries
    - Michael Rockefeller Search - Letters of Appreciation - Press (Box 95, Folder 978)
      Letters to news people who covered the search
    - Michael Rockefeller Search - Letters of Appreciation - Pan Am/KLM (Box 95, Folder 979)
      Letters to staff of airlines.
    - Michael Rockefeller Search - Letters of Appreciation - Australia (Box 96, Folder 980)
    - Michael Rockefeller Search - Plaques of Appreciation (Box 96, Folder 981)
    - Michael Rockefeller Search - Lists of Search-Related Mail (Box 96, Folder 982)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Sealed or Illegible Mail to Michael Rockefeller (later opened) (Box 96, Folder 983)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Bills and Statements, 1959-1962 (Box 96, Folder 984)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Business Correspondence after disapperance (Box 96, Folder 985)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Dutch/New Guinea Accounts (Box 96, Folder 986)
    - Michael Rockefeller - National Museum of Hollandia, New Guinea (Box 96, Folder 987)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Union Church Memorial Service, 1962 May 6 (Box 96, Folder 988)
    - Contributions in Memory of Michael Rockefeller, 1961-1969 (Box 96, Folder 989)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Memorial Suggestions - A-Z (Box 96, Folder 990)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Proposed Memorial Scholarship (Rhodes School) (Box 96, Folder 991)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Tracking Condolences (Box 96, Folder 992)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Memorial Contributions Returned (Box 96, Folder 993)
    - Michael Clark Rockefeller Memorial Fellowship (Harvard) (Box 96, Folder 994)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Memorial Fly Club, 1964 (Box 97, Folder 995)
      List of donors to memorial from Fly Club; presentation of Andrew Wyeth watercolor in memory of Michael; letters of appreciation.
    - Michael Rockefeller - Asmat Books and Notes (Box 97, Folder 996)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Asmat Book Distribution (Box 97, Folder 997)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Requests for Asmat Book (Box 97, Folder 998)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Miscellaneous Memorials, Publications, and Requests (Box 97, Folder 999)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Correspondence on his Thesis, 1965-1968 (Box 97, Folder 1000)
      Thesis - Nelson W. Aldrich and Banking Reform
    - Michael Rockefeller - Thesis Notes and Pamphlets (Box 97, Folder 1001)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Thesis Illustrations (Box 97, Folder 1002)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Thesis Notes (Box 98, Folder 1003)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Bound Thesis. Marked Copies, 1960 (Box 98, Folder 1004-1005)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Typed Script of Log of Trip to New Guinea, 1961 March-June (Box 98, Folder 1006)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Log Book (small), 1961 March-June (Box 98, Folder 1007)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Log Book (large) (Box 98, Folder 1008)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Notes from Trip with Peter (Box 99, Folder 1009)
      Notes on artifacts
    - Michael Rockefeller - Documentation of Art Objects, original (Box 99, Folder 1010)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Documentation of Art Objects, typescripts (Box 99, Folder 1011)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Trip to Lorentz and Nordwest River, typescript (Box 99, Folder 1012)
      Including field notes
    - Michael Rockefeller - First Trip to Asmat, notebook (Box 99, Folder 1013)
    - Michael Rockefeller - First Trip to Asmat, typescript (Box 99, Folder 1014)
    - Michael Rockefeller - First Trip to Asmat, Field Notes (Box 99, Folder 1015)
    - Michael Rockefeller - First Trip to Asmat, Field Notes typescript (Box 99, Folder 1016)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Sound Tape Journal, Volumes I and II (Box 100, Folder 1017-1018)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Sound Tape Journal Transcriptions (Box 100, Folder 1019)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Loose Leaf Notebook Contents (Box 100, Folder 1020)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Bibliography typescript (Box 101, Folder 1021)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Glossary of Terms (Box 101, Folder 1022)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Wallet (Box 101, Folder 1023)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Testament, 1961 (Box 101, Folder 1024)
      Inscribed by Steven Clark Rockefeller, Michael's brother.
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Photos (Box 101, Folder 1025)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Reference Publications (Box 101, Folder 1026)
      This folder is empty. It originally contained two reference publications that were badly damaged by water and mold: Three Regions of Primitive Art and Film and Its Techniques. The copies were disposed of in 2011 because they or similar information were available online.
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Publications (Box 101, Folder 1027)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Publications (Box 101, Folder 1028)
    - Michael Rockefeller Search, Chronological Report (Box 101, Folder 1029)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Cables to Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR), 1961 November 22-27 (Box 101, Folder 1030)
    - Art of the Asmat - The Collection of Michael S. Rockefeller (oversized scrapbook) (Box 102)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolences from Personal Friends (Box 103, Folder 1031)
    - Contributions in Memory of Michael Rockefeller (Box 103, Folder 1032)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - A-B (Box 103, Folder 1033-1037)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - C-Gh (Box 104, Folder 1038-1047)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Gi-K (Box 105, Folder 1048-1056)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - L-P (Box 106, Folder 1057-1066)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Q-S (Box 107, Folder 1067-1075)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - T-Z (Box 108, Folder 1076-1080)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Africa (Box 108, Folder 1081)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Canada and Caribbean (Box 108, Folder 1082)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Central and South America (Box 108, Folder 1083)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Mexico (Box 108, Folder 1084)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Belgium and Germany (Box 109, Folder 1085)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Greece, Holland, and Norway (Box 109, Folder 1086)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - British Isles (Box 109, Folder 1087)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - France (Box 109, Folder 1088)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Italy (Box 109, Folder 1089)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Portugal and Spain (Box 109, Folder 1090)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Poland and Switzerland (Box 109, Folder 1091)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Middle East (Box 109, Folder 1092)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Far East (Box 109, Folder 1093)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters/Clippings (Box 109, Folder 1094)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Acknowledgments and Undeliverable (Box 110, Folder 1095)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Special Condolence Letters - A-L (Box 110, Folder 1096)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Special Condolence Letters - M-Y (Box 110, Folder 1097)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Handwritten Condolence Responses (Box 110, Folder 1098)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Derogatory (Box 110, Folder 1099)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Foreign Crackpots (Box 110, Folder 1100)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Mystics - A-Z (and anonymous) (Box 110, Folder 1101-1104)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Foreign Mystics (Box 111, Folder 1105)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Anonymous (Box 111, Folder 1106-1110)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Sympathy Cards, no return address (Box 111, Folder 1111)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Crackpots (Box 112, Folder 1112-1115)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Second and Third Letters, no answer (Box 112, Folder 1116-1117)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Mary M. Strawbridge Condolence Responses (Box 112, Folder 1118-1119)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted - Living Rockefeller family - Family Matters - Restricted for Life
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolences - Religious Items (Box 113, Folder 1120)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolences - Religious Certificates (Box 113, Folder 1121)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolences - Religious Memorabilia (Box 113, Folder 1122)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolences - Religious and Miscellaneous Items (Box 113, Folder 1123)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolences - Miscellaneous Publications (Box 113, Folder 1124)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Miscellaneous and Condolence Items (Box 114, Folder 1125)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Unanswered - A-M (Box 114, Folder 1126-1128)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Unanswered - N-Z (Box 115, Folder 1129-1131)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - No Return Address (Box 115, Folder 1132-1133)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Unanswered, Foreign (Box 115, Folder 1134)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolence Letters - Anonymous (Box 115, Folder 1135)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Sympathy Cards (Box 116, Folder 1136-1140)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Sympathy Cards (Box 117, Folder 1141-1143)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Christmas Cards, 1961 (Box 117, Folder 1144-1146)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Christmas Cards, 1961 (Box 118, Folder 1147-1149)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Religious and Mass Cards (Box 118, Folder 1150-1151)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Religious and Mass Cards (Box 119, Folder 1152-1156)
    - Michael Rockefeller - General (Box 94, Folder 952A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - JDR Jr. Correspondence (Box 94, Folder 957A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - New Guinea Correspondence with Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR) (Box 94, Folder 960A)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR) Correspondence following disappearance (Box 95, Folder 967A-968A)
    - Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR) New Guinea Trip, 1961 November (Box 95, Folder 972A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Bills and Statements, 1959-1962 (Box 96, Folder 984A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Union Church Memorial Service, 1962 May 6 (Box 96, Folder 988A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Memorial Suggestions - A-Z (Box 96, Folder 990A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Proposed Memorial Scholarship (Rhodes School) (Box 96, Folder 991A)
    - Michael Clark Rockefeller Memorial Fellowship (Harvard) (Box 96, Folder 994A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Memorial Fly Club, 1964 (Box 97, Folder 995A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Asmat Books and Notes (Box 97, Folder 996A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Asmat Book Distribution (Box 97, Folder 997A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Requests for Asmat Book (Box 97, Folder 998A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Miscellaneous Memorials, Publications, and Requests (Box 97, Folder 999A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Correspondence on his Thesis, 1965-1968 (Box 97, Folder 1000A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Cables to Nelson A. Rockefeller (NAR), 1961 November 22-27 (Box 101, Folder 1030A)
    - Michael Rockefeller - Condolences from Personal Friends (Box 103, Folder 1031A)
- Michael C. Rockefeller photographs, 2
  This series contains photographs taken by and of Nelson A. Rockefeller's son Michael on his two expeditions to the Asmat region of New Guinea in 1961. There are no images of Nelson A. Rockefeller or the later search for Michael.
  - Color Slides
    - Untitled, 1003 (Box 1, Roll 1003)
    - Untitled, 1010 (Box 1, Roll 1010)
    - Untitled, 1001 (Box 1, Roll 1001)
    - Untitled, 1036 (Box 1, Roll 1036)
    - Untitled (Box 1, Roll 1018-1020)
    - Untitled, 1023 (Box 1, Roll 1023)
    - Untitled (Box 1, Roll 1025-1032)
    - Untitled, 1035 (Box 1, Roll 1035)
    - Copies I-VII (Box 1)
  - Black and White Prints, black and white prints, 3 1/4 4 1/2 inch
    - Untitled, 102 (Box 2, Roll 102)
    - Untitled, 288 (Box 2, Roll 288)
    - Untitled, 295 (Box 2, Roll 295)
    - Asmat and aerials, 296 (Box 2, Roll 296)
    - Untitled, 1001 (Box 2, Roll 1001)
    - Dance in Jeu at Ammanamkai, 1002 (297) (Box 2, Roll 1002)
    - Untitled, 1003 (Box 2, Roll 1003)
    - Women in tent; Baliem, 1004 (298) (Box 2, Roll 1004)
    - Dance in Jeu, 1005 (299) (Box 2, Roll 1005)
    - Strobe of dance, 1006 (300) (Box 2, Roll 1006)
    - Dance in Jeu, 1007 (301) (Box 2, Roll 1007)
    - Canoe display Ammanamkai (302-303) (Box 2, Roll 1008-1009)
    - Untitled, 1010 (Box 2, Roll 1010)
    - Canoe display Ammanamkai (304-305) (Box 2, Roll 1011-1012)
    - Canoes; Jeu in Awok-strobe, 1013 (306) (Box 2, Roll 1013)
    - Jeu in Awok-Strobe (307-309) (Box 2, Roll 1014-1016)
    - Dancing in Jeu-Strobe, 1017 (310) (Box 2, Roll 1017)
    - Untitled (Box 2, Roll 1018-1020)
    - Strobe-dancing in Jeu; south, 1021 (311) (Box 2, Roll 1021)
    - Omadasep's artists; dance of bisj poles; moonlight pic.poles, 1022 (312) (Box 2, Roll 1022)
    - Untitled, 1023 (Box 3, Roll 1023)
    - Jeu Aman and Ammanamgai, 1024 (313) (Box 3, Roll 1024)
    - Untitled (Box 3, Roll 1025-1032)
    - Bisj pole ceremony; dancing in jeus; objects in jeu, 1033 (314) (Box 3, Roll 1033)
    - Artists of bisj poles at Omadisep; bisj poles at Ochinep, 1034 (315) (Box 3, Roll 1034)
    - Untitled (Box 3, Roll 1035-1037)
    - Bisj poles at Atsjametsj, 1038 (316) (Box 3, Roll 1038)
    - Ammanamgai, 1039 (317) (Box 3, Roll 1039)
    - Untitled, 1040 (318) (Box 3, Roll 1040)
    - Copies (Box 3)
    - Photographs by Charles Uht of D. Newton Installation (Box 3)
  - Color Negatives, color negatives, 2 1/2 3 1/4 inch
    - Untitled, 102 (Box 4, Roll 102)
    - Untitled, 1001 (Box 4, Roll 1001)
    - Untitled, 1003 (Box 4, Roll 1003)
    - Dance in Jeu, 1007 (301) (Box 4, Roll 1007)
    - Untitled, 1010 (Box 4, Roll 1010)
    - Untitled (Box 4, Roll 1018-1020)
    - Untitled, 1023 (Box 4, Roll 1023)
    - Untitled (Box 4, Roll 1025-1032)
    - Untitled, 1035 (Box 4, Roll 1035)
    - Untitled, 1036 (Box 4, Roll 1036)
    - Images from The Asmat of New Guinea (Box 4)
  - Black and White negatives, black and white negatives, 35 mm.
    - Asmat and aerials, 296 (Box 5, Roll 296)
    - Dance in Jeu at Ammanamkai, 1002 (297) (Box 5, Roll 1002)
    - Women in tent; Baliem, 1004 (298) (Box 5, Roll 1004)
    - Dance in Jeu, 1005 (299) (Box 5, Roll 1005)
    - Strobe of dance, 1006 (300) (Box 5, Roll 1006)
    - Canoe display Ammanamkai (302-303) (Box 5, Roll 1008-1009)
    - Canoe display Ammanamkai (304-305) (Box 5, Roll 1011-1012)
    - Canoes; Jeu in Awok-strobe, 1013 (306) (Box 5, Roll 1013)
    - Jeu in Awok; Strobe (307-309) (Box 5, Roll 1014-1016)
    - Dancing in Jeu-Strobe, 1017 (310) (Box 5, Roll 1017)
    - Strobe-dancing in Jeu; south, 1021 (311) (Box 5, Roll 1021)
    - Omadasep's artists; dance of bisj poles; moonlight pic.poles, 1022 (312) (Box 5, Roll 1022)
    - Jeu Aman and Ammanamgai, 1024 (313) (Box 5, Roll 1024)
    - Bisj pole ceremony; dancing in jeus; objects in jeu, 1033 (314) (Box 5, Roll 1033)
    - Artists of bisj poles at Omadisep; bisj poles at Ochinep, 1034 (315) (Box 5, Roll 1034)
    - Bisj poles at Atsjametsj, 1038 (316) (Box 5, Roll 1038)
    - Ammanamgai, 1039 (317) (Box 5, Roll 1039)
    - Untitled, 1040 (318) (Box 5, Roll 1040)
  - Oversized Black and White Prints
    - Black and White Prints (Box 6)
  - Production of Book, The Asmat of New Guinea: The Journal of Michael Clark Rockefeller (New York: The Museum of Primitive Art, 1962)
    - Paste-up page layouts of the "Journal Section" of The Asmat (Box 7, Folder 132)
    - Photoprint page layouts for The Asmat made by A.A. Gerbrands (Box 7, Folder 133)
    - Correspondence between parties involved in publishing The Asmat (Box 7, Folder 134)
    - Paste-up print copy of The Asmat, hard cover (black) (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - Dutch language journal of trip to New Guinea 1943 with photos (Box 8, Folder 136)
      Background material on the area, acquired by Michael Rockefeller as a reference source for his travels in New Guinea.